
<?xml-model href="schemas/lglc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="schemas/lglc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m">Lesbian and Gay Liberation in Canada</title>
        <editor>
          <persName sameAs="people.xml#MSCH">
            <forename>Michelle</forename>
            <surname>Schwartz</surname>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <persName sameAs="people.xml#CCRO">
            <forename>Constance</forename>
            <surname>Crompton</surname>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared by</resp>
          <persName sameAs="people.xml#">
            <forename>Caitlin</forename>
            <surname>Voth</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName sameAs="people.xml#">
            <forename><!-- your first name --></forename>
            <surname><!-- your last name --></surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title level="m">Lesbian and Gay Liberation In Canada: A Selected Annotated Chronology,
              1976-1981</title>
            <author>
              <persName sameAs="people.xml#DMCL">
                <forename>McLeod</forename>
                <surname>Donald</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>EWC Press/ Homewood Books</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>
            <date>1996</date>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <listEvent n="1981">
        <event xml:id="n81.1">
          <p> Montréal Amazons Then, Lesbians Now/Amazones d’hier, lesbiennes d’aujourd’hui, a
            one-hour-and-forty-five-minute video made for lesbians only and surveying the state of
            lesbian life in Montréal, was released by Video Amazone. </p>
          <bibl>“Amazones d’hier, lesbiennes d’aujourd’hui,” Le Berdache, no. 25 (1981), p. 8</bibl>
          <bibl> “Amazons Then, Lesbians Now,” Lesbian/Lesbienne, 1, no. 3 (1981): 4.</bibl>

        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.14">
          <p> Vancouver Scott Watson’s book of stories Platonic Love: Three Tales of Language and
            Desire was published by New Star Books. </p>
          <bibl>Don Larventz, “The Fiction of Sexual Truth” (review), Body Politic, no. 78 (1981),
            p. 33</bibl>
          <bibl> Don Officer, “Beyond the Point” (review), Books in Canada, January 1982, pp.
            15–16</bibl>
          <bibl> Gerry Oxford, “Platonic Love” (review), Quill &amp; Quire, January 1982, pp.
            31–32</bibl>
          <bibl> Simon Ruddell, “Street Life” (review), Canadian Literature, no. 95 (1982), pp.
            143–44</bibl>
          <bibl> Ian Young, The Male Homosexual in Literature: A Bibliography, second ed. (Metuchen,
            N.J.: Scarecrow Press, 1982), entry 4013.</bibl>

        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.30">
          <p> January 26 Toronto Lynne Lake, the mother of two schoolchildren, reopened debate on
            sexual orientation bias at the Toronto Board of Education when she made an emotional
            plea to the schools programs committee. Lake demanded that the trustees rescind a motion
            passed September 18, 1980, which prohibited “bias on the basis of sex or sexual
            orientation,” and which specifically permitted “discussion of homosexuality” in schools.
            Lake also claimed that the NDP had been “exploiting the (gay) issue” and that gay
            activist John Argue, the chairman of the Metro Toronto NDP, had used political pressure
            to swing the vote in favour of the anti-discrimination motion. After some vigorous
            debate, the issue was referred to a special meeting of the full board of education to be
            held February 23, 1981. (See also February 23, 1981.) </p>
          <bibl>Rick Brennan, “No Homosexual Lesson for Her Kids,” Toronto Star, four star ed., 17
            February 1981, p. C18</bibl>
          <bibl> Virginia Corner, “Homosexual Issue Revived by Mom’s Ire,” Toronto Star, four star
            ed., 27 January 1981, p. A3</bibl>
          <bibl> Bruce A. McLeod, “Mom Battles Board Over Stand on Gays,” Toronto Sun, 17 February
            1981, p. 18</bibl>
          <bibl> Roger Spalding, “Mother’s Plea to School Board Reopens Debate on Ban on Bias,” Body
            Politic, no. 71 (1981), p. 13.</bibl>

        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.35">
          <p> January–February Ottawa The Ottawa Children’s Aid Society (CAS) confirmed that it
            <!-- I'm the greatest --> would consider placing children with homosexual foster
            parents, but only as a last resort. Preference was to be given to placing children in a
            “normalized setting,” with heterosexual parents. Roger Galipeau, president of GO, called
            the policy discriminatory and asked CAS to reconsider its position. </p>
          <bibl>David Garmaise, “Gay Foster Parents a Last Resort: CAS,” Body Politic, no. 71
            (1981), p. 14.</bibl>

        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.71">
          <p> February 23 Toronto Three weeks of public hearings on Bill 209, an Act to Amend the
            Ontario Human Rights Code, were slated to begin before the Social Development Committee
            of the Ontario Legislature. </p>
          <bibl>Chris Bearchell, “Strange Bedfellows?” Body Politic, no. 70 (1981), pp.
            10–11.</bibl>

        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.72">
          <p> February 23 Toronto The Toronto Board of Education overturned two resolutions to ban
            discrimination against gays it had instituted in September 1980, by a vote of fourteen
            to twelve, and replaced them with more conservative ones. Thirty-eight speakers
            addressed the full board meeting, which lasted more than seven hours. The trustees voted
            twenty-two to four to outlaw discrimination against gays in the board’s employment
            practices only, and also agreed to allow discussion of homosexuality in schools but only
            under strict guidelines, “when conducted by teachers and appropriate board staff as (the
            topic) arises out of curriculum.” </p>
          <bibl>Merylie Houston, “A Parent Speaks Out: The Gay Issue at the Board: The Latest
            Round,” Mudpie (Toronto), 2, no. 3 (March 1981): 2</bibl>
          <bibl> “Pros and Cons Clash over Gays in Classroom: Education Board Debate,” Toronto Sun,
            24 February 1981, p. 31</bibl>
          <bibl> Roger Spalding, “Toronto Board Limits Gay Rights Policy,” Body Politic, no. 72
            (1981), p. 14</bibl>
          <bibl> Allan Sparrow, “Sexual Orientation: 2 Battles Won. Board of Education Re-affirms
            Stand Opposing Discrimination on the Basis of Sexual Orientation,” Ward 6 News
            (Toronto), March 1981, p. 5</bibl>
          <bibl> “Toronto Enrolment Drop Predicted over Homosexuals,” Toronto Star, four star ed.,
            25 February 1981, p. A5</bibl>
          <bibl> Julia Turner, “Board Hears All Views on Homosexual Issue,” Globe and Mail, metro
            ed., 24 February 1981, p. 19</bibl>
          <bibl> Julia Turner, “Gay Rights Are Upheld by Board,” Globe and Mail, metro ed., 25
            February 1981, p. 5</bibl>
          <bibl> David Vienneau, “Trustees Spurn, Back Homosexuals,” Toronto Star, four star ed., 24
            February 1981, pp. A1, A7.</bibl>

        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.128">
          <p> Spring Halifax The first issue of Making Waves: An Atlantic Quarterly for Lesbians and
            Gay Men was published. Robin Metcalfe edited the magazine. </p>
          <bibl>Arn Gabel, “Make Way for Making Waves,” Body Politic, no. 70 (1981), p. 12</bibl>
          <bibl> Robin Metcalfe, “Making Waves in Atlantic Canada,” Body Politic, no. 74 (1981), p.
            17</bibl>
          <bibl> “New: Making Waves,” Fredericton FLAGMAG, no. 4 (1981), p. 7.</bibl>


        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.190">
          <p> May 16–18 Vancouver More than 500 women participated in the fifth Bi-national Lesbian
            Conference, held at Langara College. The event drew women from across Canada to discuss
            priorities such as childcare, fighting the Right, and the formation of a national
            lesbian organization. There were plenary sessions, workshops, an art display (“Woman to
            Woman,” at the Women in Focus Gallery), and a dance featuring the lesbian rock band Mama
            Quilla II (with Lorraine Segato). More than 200 women marched in Canada’s first lesbian
            pride march, from Robson Square through downtown Vancouver to the WECC. A final report,
            Lesbian Power: Organizing for the 80s, was published after the conference. </p>
          <bibl>“1981 Bi-national Lesbian Vandykescouver, B.C., Conference!” Lavender Sheets (LOOT),
            Summer 1980, p. (3)</bibl>
          <bibl> “1981 Lesbian Conference,” Gaze, June 1981, p. (4)</bibl>
          <bibl> 1981 Lesbian Conference Committee, “1981 Lesbian Conference,” VGCC News, 2, no. 3
            (March 1981): 16</bibl>
          <bibl> Chris Bearchell, “Lesbian Pride March Is a First for Canada,” Body Politic, no. 74
            (1981), p. 10</bibl>
          <bibl> R.C., “Vancouver Lesbian Conference,” Making Waves (Halifax), no. 2 (1981), p.
            7</bibl>
          <bibl> Diane Fisher, “1981 Lesbian Conference: Proposals from Workshops at the
            Conference,” Gaze, September 1981, pp. (5–7) and Gaze, November 1981, pp. (5–7)</bibl>
          <bibl> Maureen FitzGerald and Daphne Morrison, “Lesbian Conference: Agony and Audacity,”
            Broadside, 2, no. 9 (July 1981): 4</bibl>
          <bibl> Margaret Fulford, ed., The Canadian Women’s Movement, 1960–1990: A Guide to
            Archival Resources/Le mouvement canadien des femmes, 1960–1990: guide de ressources
            archivistiques (Toronto: Canadian Women’s Movement Archives/ECW Press, 1992), entry
            67</bibl>
          <bibl> Dorothy Kidd, “1981 Lesbian Conference,” VGCC News, 2, no. 6 (June 1981): 14</bibl>


        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.223">
          <p> June 5 Atlanta, Ga. The Centers for Disease Control (CDC) reported that five gay men
            in Los Angeles had been diagnosed with pneumocystis pneumonia, which was rare and
            frequently fatal. This was the first official report from the CDC concerning the health
            crisis that would later become known as the AIDS pandemic. (See also July 3, 1981.) </p>
          <bibl>Bill Lewis and Randy Coates, “Moral Lessons</bibl>
          <bibl> Fatal Cancer,” Body Politic, no. 77 (1981), p. 43</bibl>
          <bibl> Jacques Pepin, The Origins of AIDS (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2011),
            293 pp.</bibl>

        </event>
        <event xml:id="n81.273">
          <p> July 3 New York, N.Y. The New York Times published an article by Lawrence K. Altman
            entitled “Rare Cancer Seen in 41 Homosexuals,” which was subsequently distributed
            internationally by the New York Times News Service. This was the first major mainstream
            newspaper article to discuss the health crisis that would eventually become known as the
            AIDS pandemic. An unnamed Body Politic reporter (likely Randy Coates and/or Bill Lewis)
            dismissed the report as being biased and riddled with errors. </p>
          <bibl>Lawrence K. Altman, “Rare Cancer Seen in 41 Homosexuals,” New York Times, late city
            ed., 3 July 1981, p. A20</bibl>
          <bibl> Alain Emmanuel Dreuilhe, “Le cancer gai” (medical column), Le Berdache, no. 24
            (1981), p. 23</bibl>


        </event>


      </listEvent>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
